Guide to the William Ivey Cranford Papers, circa 1889-1945
Duke University. University Archives
William Ivey Cranford papers circa 1889-1945
Duke University. University Archives
Cranford, William Ivey.
3.75 linear feet Extent: 3,250 Items
William Ivey Cranford was Dean of Trinity College. He resigned as Dean on June 4, 1917 and was succeeded by William H. Wannamaker. Collection contains notebooks, correspondence, notes, transcripts and manuscripts. Material ranges in date from circa circa 1889-1945, with many of the materials undated.
RL.01478
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The William Ivey Cranford Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1973, 1977, and 2007.
Biographical Note
William Ivey (W.I.) Cranford was born November 10, 1867 in Ophir, North Carolina. His parents were Joshua A. Cranford and Mary E. Davis. He entered Trinity College (Randolph County) in 1887 and graduated with an A. B. degree in 1891. He received his Ph.D. from Yale University in 1895 and was soon thereafter married to Nellie Edwards. They were the first Trinity graduates to marry each other. He returned to Trinity in 1898 and was professor philosophy and Greek. He held the Carr Professor of Philosophy until his death. In 1910, Professor Cranford was appointed Dean of Trinity College and served in that position until 1917. He died in Durham on August 29, 1936.
Collection Overview
Collection contains correspondence, Cranford's notebooks from graduate courses at Yale University, transcripts and notes from articles on, mentioning, or by Cranford (with notes taken by H. E. Kolbe), transcripts and notes from papers and lectures by Cranford (notes by Kolbe), manuscripts, miscellaneous notes and drafts for articles and lectures, material collected by Kolbe on Cranford, and a school notebook (circa 1790s) which is believed to have been from the Edwards family. A bulk of the correspondence (primarily from 1893-1895 and 1905), is personal and includes letters written by and to William Cranford, including many to and from Nellie Edwards, who later became his wife. Also included are numerous letters from Mrs. Mary Jane Edwards (M.J.Edwards), Nellie's mother, to William Cranford while he was attending Yale University in New Haven, Connecticut, and letters to Nellie Edwards from a variety of close friends and former students. The correspondence is arranged chronologically. One folder consists of miscellaneous materials such as receipts, miniature sheet music, and samples of steel pens from Perry & Co's Steel Pens.
Much of the correspondence, loose sheets, and notebooks are fragile and should be handled with care. The material ranges in date from circa 1889-1934, with many of the materials undated.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Yale University -- Students.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts, American -- North Carolina -- Durham.; Lectures and lecturing.; School notebooks.
Related Material
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004.
University Archives. Duke University.
Biographical Reference Collection, 1972-2004.
University Archives. Duke University.
Inventory of the Henry E. Kolbe Papers, 1928-1934.
University Archives. Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 2 Boxes
  - Dr. Cranford's notebooks from Yale University, circa 1893-1895 (Box 1)
    - Introduction to Philosophy
    - Psychology
    - Psychology of Education
    - Readings in Philosphy
    - 5 unlabled philosophy notebooks
  - Manuscripts, undated
  - Manuscripts, undated
  - Notes for articles and lectures, circa 1889, undated
  - Notes for articles and lectures, undated
  - Notes for articles and lectures, 1898-1907, undated
  - Kolbe's research and miscellaneous correspondence, 1933-1934 (Box 2)
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from A.R. Miller, Trinity College, June 11, 1892 (Box 3)
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., February 19, 1893
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Kinston, N.C., August 7, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Durham, N.C., August 16, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Mary Jane Edwards (M.J.Edwards), Durham, N.C., September 10, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., September 11, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., September 17, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, Durham, N.C., September 24, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., September 26, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., October 1, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, Durham, N.C., October 7, 1893
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Kinston, N.C., October 20, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., October 20, 1893
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Kinston, N.C., October 21, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, Durham, N.C., October 21, 1893
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Phoebe, Kinston, N.C., October 27, 1893
  - Letter to Professor W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., October 31, 1893
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Kinston, N.C., November 2, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, Durham, N.C., November 4, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., November 12, 1893
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Fannie[?], Kinston, N.C., November 13, 1893
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Miss Lizzie, Kinston, N.C., November 14, 1893
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Rev. Kennedy, Georgeville, N.C., November 17, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., November 21, 1893
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Kinston, N.C., November 22, 1893
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Phoebe, Kinston, N.C., November 24, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, Durham, N.C., November 27, 1893
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Kinston, N.C., November 28, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards & "Unknown Friend", Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., December 4, 1893
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., December 10, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., December 11, 1893
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., January 4, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Fannie, Kinston, N.C., January 9, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Kinston, N.C., January 9, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Mary Jane Edwards (M.J. Edwards), January 24, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., January 26, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, February 3, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., February 6, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Kinston, N.C., February 6, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, Durham, N.C., February 10, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Durham, N.C., February 12, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Kinston, N.C., February 13, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Kinston, N.C., February 19, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., February 26, 1894
  - Letter to [?] from [?], March, 1894 (Box 4)
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., March 5, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Ida, Kinston, N.C., March 9, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., March 12, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Kinston, N.C., March 13, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, Durham, N.C., March 17, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., March 20, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., March 31, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, Durham, N.C., March 31, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from The Niagara Laundry Co., March 31, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., April 8, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., April 13, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, Durham, N.C., April 14, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Kinston, N.C., April 18, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from May, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., April 19, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., April 22, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Kinston, N.C., April 23, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, Durham, N.C., April 27, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Kinston, N.C., April 30, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, Durham, N.C., May [?], 1894
  - Letter to Professor W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., May 7, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., May 15, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Rev. Kennedy, Georgeville, N.C., May 18, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., May 22, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from J.W. Kennedy, Kinston, N.C., May 25, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from George Trumball Ladd, Ophir, N.C., June 30, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., July 3, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Ophir, N.C., July 5, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., July 9, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Fannie, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., July 10, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Ophir, N.C., July 16, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., July 18, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Fannie B., Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., July 19, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, Fayet[te]ville, N.C., July 20, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., July 25, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Lizzie, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., July 28, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Fannie, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., July 20, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Francie Williams, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., September 19, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., September 29, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., October 10, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., October 12, 1894
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from "May", Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., October 13, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., October 14, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., October 19, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., October 22, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., October 25, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., October 30, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., November 5, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., November 13, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., November 14, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., November 25, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., November 26, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., December 3, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., December 16, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., December 19, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., December 22, 1894
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., January 3, 1895 (Box 5)
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Mary Jane Edwards (M.J. Edwards), New Haven, C.T., January 6, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., January 10, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., January 18, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., January 20, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., January 28, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., February 1, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., February 7, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., February 3, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., February 14, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., February 17, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., February 26, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., March 3, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., March 9, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., March 15, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., March 17, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., March 21, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., March 26, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., March 28, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., March 29, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., April 3, 1895
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Fannie, Kinston, N.C., April 4, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., April 7, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., April 15, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., April 16, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., April 21, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., April 24, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., May 2, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Olin Boggess, New Haven, C.T., May 5, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., May 6, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., May 7, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from V. Ballard, New Haven, C.T., May 17, 1895
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Carrie Carpenter, Durham, N.C., May 19, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., May 19, 1895
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from W.I. Cranford, Durham, N.C., May 22, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., May 24, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., May 27, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from C. Ironmonger (Seaboard Air Line), New Haven, C.T., June 6, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Frank Armfield, New Haven, C.T., June 7, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from M.J. Edwards, New Haven, C.T., June 11, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Nellie Edwards, New Haven, C.T., June 11, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Davidson[?], Ophir, N.C., June 18, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Willa[?] and Mittie[?], Ophir, N.C., June 18, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from George Lance, Ophir, N.C., June 22, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Charles E. Turner, Ophir, N.C., July 2, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Chas[?] Rapon[?], Ophir, N.C., July 5, 1895
  - Letter to Professor and Mrs. W.I. Cranford from Flowers[?], Ophir, N.C., July 21, 1895
  - Letter to W.I. Cranford from Carrie Carpenter, Trinity College, N.C., August 13, 1895
  - Letter to Nellie Edwards from Mrs. M. Womble, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., May 28, 1896
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Trinity Park, Durham, N.C., July 27, 1897
  - Postcard to W.I. Cranford from J.C.[?], Durham, N.C., 1905 (Box 6)
  - Letters to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., September 5-7, 1905
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., September 9, 1905
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., September 10, 1905
  - Letters to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., September 12-13, 1905
  - Letters to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., September 13-16, 1905
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., September 17, 1905
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., September 19, 1905
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., September 21, 1905
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., September 22, 1905
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., September 23, 1905
  - Letters to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., September 24-25, 1905
  - Letters to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., September 27-29, 1905
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., September 30, 1905
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., October [?], 1905 (Box 7)
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., October 1, 1905
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., October 3, 1905
  - Letters to Mrs. W.I. Cranford and daughter Mary White Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., October 4, 1905
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., October 5, 1905
  - Letters to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., October 6-7, 1905
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., October 9, 1905
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., October 10, 1905
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., October 11, 1905
  - Letters to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., October 12-14, 1905
  - Letters to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., October 15-16, 1905
  - Letters to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., October 23-25, 1905
  - Letters to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, Waynesville, N.C., October 26-27, 1905
  - Letter to Mrs. W.I. Cranford from W.I. Cranford, undated
  - Letters to Nellie Edwards from unknown, Burlington, N.C., Kinston, N.C., May 30, 1893-December 27, 1894
  - Associated Collegiate Press of N.S.P.A. Award, 1938-1939, 1945
  - Miscellaneous materials, undated
  - Mathematic Notebook of William White, circa 1790s (Box 8)
  - Gradebook and journal, circa 1893, early 1900's